[Music]
a series of papers published in the
annals of internal medicine that largely
discounted all but the highest quality
randomized studies
reached a conclusion directly contrary
to the public health advice we've heard
for years
they suggested that we should continue
our current consumption of both red and
processed meat
the authors based their exclusion of
evidence on the so-called grade criteria
which would mainly develop for
evaluating evidence from drug trials we
need randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trials for drugs but
strictness of these criteria would
probably cause evidence for just about
every
dietary lifestyle and environmental
factor related to chronic disease to be
graded as low or very low evidence
if the grade criteria were used to
evaluate the evidence for other factors
related to diets such as
inadequate fruits and vegetables or too
much soda or alcohol or whether or not
exercise is good or safe sex or sleep
smoking air pollution none of the
current recommendations on these issues
would be supported by high or even
moderate quality evidence using the drug
trial criteria
but even after ignoring major parts of
the available evidence they still found
an association between meat intake and
an increased risk of cancer and not just
cancer they found that adherence to
dietary patterns lower in red or
processed meat intake may result in a
decreased risk for premature death
cardio metabolic disease and mortality
meaning the risk of getting and dying of
diseases like heart disease and type 2
diabetes as well as the risk of getting
cancer and dying from cancer yet they
still concluded in their dietary
guideline recommendations continue your
current red meat consumption continue
your processed meat consumption forget
the whole premature death thing cancer
heart disease diabetes just keep eating
your burgers and bacon
so you have these dietary guidelines
developed by some self-appointed panel
that are tantamount to promoting meat
consumption despite their own findings
that high consumption is harmful to
health how do they square that
contradicting the evidence generated
from their own meta-analyses
there's only one body of evidence they
found the same risk that all the other
reviews found so they're not saying meat
is less risky they're just saying the
risk is acceptable
well
you do have to consider
the risks and
benefits well we've covered the harms
their own data show that a moderate
reduction in red and processed meat
consumption can reduce total mortality
by 13
heart disease mortality by 14 cancer
mortality by 11 and type 2 diabetes risk
by 24
what are the benefits
in short omnivores enjoy
eating meat
uh
okay
given people's attachment to their
meat-based diet the associated risk
reduction in our leading killers like
cancer heart disease diabetes is not
likely to provide sufficient motivation
to reduce consumption of red meat or
processed meat so therefore
eat up
in fact they even say straight out that
unlike the other dietary guidelines
suggesting we limit consumption of stuff
because of like the cancer thing
these other guidelines have paid little
of no attention to the reasons people
eat meat whereas they did a systematic
review of preferences regarding meat
consumption and
people who eat meat
enjoy eating meat
maybe that's even why they do it
they're generally unwilling to change
their meat consumption even in response
to health concerns so the panel belief
the panel you'll remember with generous
support of a group getting millions
every year from the meat industry
the panel believed that for the majority
of individuals the desirable effects
like lowering your risk of family
devastating cancer and heart attacks
associated with reducing meat
consumption
probably do not outweigh the undesirable
effects like having to give up all that
yummy meat
this is what led them to make their
recommendation to continue current
consumption
that sounds like something straight out
of the journal meat science
why should we keep eating red meat
because of the enjoyment
people also like to smoke they like to
drink soda they like to have unsafe sex
it's kind of like saying we know
motorcycle helmets can save lives but
some people still prefer the feeling of
wind in their hair so let's just tell
people to not wear helmets
but you'll actually see this argument
complying with dietary recommendations
imposes a taste cost
on consumers so how about socially
desirable dietary recommendations that
are most compatible with consumer
preferences
you know that best balance health
benefits against taste cost
so like hey even if science told us that
eating butter is unhealthy its taste
justifies the continuation of using it
what do you expect from nutrarex the
meat industry partnered panel that also
published the paper criticizing the
sugar guidelines funded by the soda and
candy industries they aim to produce
nutritional guideline recommendations
based on the preferences of patients
so what's next just telling people to
eat donuts and ice cream all day
get the animals publish the meat papers
with a press release saying no need to
reduce red or processed meat consumption
for good health
using the same methodology and rationale
they might as well have said no need to
quit smoking for good health or no need
to exercise for good health
as dr katz director of yale's prevention
research center put it
guidelines opposing the very data on
which they purport to be based are not
science they are
anti-science
[Music]
you